Finding Aid for the Robert Ardrey Papers LSC.0957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robert Ardrey papers
1935-1960
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ardrey, Robert
LSC.0957
1.6 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Robert Ardrey (1908-1970) was born in Chicago, Illinois. He studied the natural and social sciences at University of Chicago and lectured on anthropology for two years, but later found himself more interested in drama. He became a playwright and a Hollywood screenwriter. The collection consists of correspondence, clippings, ephemera and scripts.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Ardrey, 1963.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994622183606533
Biography
Robert Ardrey was born October 16, 1908 in Chicago; studied natural and social sciences at University of Chicago and lectured on anthropology for two years, but later found himself more interested in drama, where he was influenced by Thornton Wilder; his first plays had brief runs, but led to his becoming a Hollywood screenwriter, 1938; wrote film scripts, novels, and plays, including Thunder Rock, which was successful in London and filmed in Hollywood; returned to the study of anthropology in 1955, and later produced four works: African Genesis (1961), The Territorial Imperative (1966), The Social Contract (1970), and The Hunting Hypothesis (1976) all arguing that man was innately aggressive creature; continued to write screenplays, including Khartoum; finished autobiography shortly before his death in Kalk Bay, South Africa in 1980.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of letters from Ardrey to his wife and children, business correspondence, theater and motion picture scripts, and financial records. Of particular interest are several letters written by Ardrey during the era of the Hollywood blacklist, in which he refuted allegations that he was a Communist. There is also a copy of a long letter Ardrey wrote to Elia Kazan just before Kazan's appearance before the House Committee on Un-American Activities.
Organization and Arrangement
Folders are in the order determined by the previous archivist.
Screenwriters -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; Film scripts.; Ardrey, Robert--Archives.
- Ephemera, 1930-1959; 16 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content
  Includes press sheet for Quentin Durward (MGM, 1955).
- Newspaper clippings, 1954-1959; 25 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Office of War Information scripts, 1943; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, undated; 64 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Stevenson Story, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes research and script material for a campaign film for Adlai Stevenson's 1952 presidential run.
- X-ray pictures of Ardrey, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- God and Texas -- one-act playscript, ca. 1943; 23 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 1, Folder 7)
- How to Get Tough About it -- two playscripts, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- House on Fire -- playscript, undated; 118 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Eric Batter -- playscript and notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Casey Jones -- playscript, 1936; 130 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Jeb -- playscript, 1945; 131 leaves. Typescript (carbon) with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Leuchtfeuer (German translation of Thunder Rock) -- published playscript, 1954; 112 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- My Friends and I -- playscript, undated; 132 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Salome (Columbia, 1963) -- screenplay, undated; 201 leaves. Typescript on loose sheets. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Shadow of Heroes -- playscript, 1958; 127 pp. Mimeographed. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sometimes I Love You (MGM, unproduced) -- screenplay, 1951; 138 leaves. Mimeographed. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Strangerman's Bay -- playscript, undated; 83 leaves. Typescript on loose sheets. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Fenelon by Emmet Lavery (Munich, Germany: Densch) [inscribed by the author], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence with Brandt & Brandt Literary Agents, 1934-1937; 49 items. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with George Abbott, 1935; 23 items. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence relating to business and the Guggenheim Fellowship, 1936-1937; 41 items. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes letters from Harold Clurman and Theresa Helburn.
- Correspondence, personal, 1943; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes handwritten letter from Thornton Wilder.
- Correspondence, personal, 1946-1950; 20 items. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Includes copy of a letter from Ardrey to Esther Bonner, headmistress of his son's school, who had accused him of being a Communist.
- Correspondence, personal, 1951; 30 items. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Includes copy of a letter from Ardrey to Esther Bonner denying that he is a Communist; copy of a letter from Ardrey to Elia "Gadg" Kazan about Kazan's upcoming appearance before HUAC, March 22, 1952; letter from Michael Redgrave.
- Correspondence, personal, 1952; 10 items. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes note from Adlai Stevenson, December 11, 1952.
- Correspondence, personal, 1953; 44 items. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Includes post card from William Shirer; letter from Montgomery Clift
- Correspondence, personal, 1954; 14 items. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence relating to loyalty, 1954; 9 items. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Includes copy of a letter from Ardrey to MGM refuting allegations that he is a Communist, so that he can work on Quentin Durward; copy of a letter from Ardrey to the California Committee on Un-American Activities defending his participation in the Committee for the First Amendment.
- Correspondence, personal, 1955; 28 items. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, business, 1956-1967; 33 items. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, personal, 1956-1958; 30 items. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, personal, 1959; 7 items. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, personal, undated; 25 items. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Christmas cards, circa 1953; 18 items. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Includes three cards from Michael Redgrave and family; card from Fredric March and Florence Eldridge.
- Contracts and related correspondence, 1931-1938; 15 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Contracts and related correspondence, 1944-1947; 7 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Business and tax records, 1950; 22 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Business and tax records, 1951; 44 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Business and tax records, 1956; 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Business and tax records, 1957; 29 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Business and tax records, 1958; 19 items. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Bank stubs, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Bank stubs, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)